Guide to the Adler Family Papers, 1893-1992 (bulk 1920-1977)
P-890
- Series VI: Programs and Announcements, 1928-1929, 1958-1961, undated; 2 folders
  - Lazar Freed, 1928, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series VII: Memorabilia and Miscellaneous Publications, 1917-1936, 1970-1972, undated; 5 folders,; 1 oversize (OS1) box
  Series VII contains miscellaneous writings and correspondence largely lacking attribution and an assortment of memorabilia from the lives of Celia Adler and Lazar Freed. Box 2 Folder 10 contains Adler’s lifetime membership card for the Yiddish Theatrical Alliance and her Social Security card from 1936. It also contains a Jewish National Fund Certificate given in Lazar Freed’s honor in 1924, and a 1919 play published in Leipzig by Karl Schonherr. Box 2 Folder 12 includes Adler’s honorary membership card for the Hebrew Actors’ Union. Box 3 contains collections of sheet music in Yiddish, English, Russian and German, and four elaborate volumes on the subject of the Russian theatre. It is not known to whom these oversized items originally belonged, but all were published between the years of 1893 and 1928.
  - Miscellaneous Writings and Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Memorabilia: Yiddish Theatrical Alliance Card, Kindertragodie, JNF Certificate, Social Security Card, 1917- 1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Memorabilia and Miscellaneous Publications: Greater Recording Company Catalog, Calendar of the National Women’s League of the United Synagogue of America, Forverts, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Memorabilia and Miscellaneous Publications: Hebrew Actors’ Union Card, Theater A.D. Wien, Ashmeday, Booklet of Chaliapin’s Lyrics, Excerpts from a Book on the Yiddish Theater, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sheet Music in Yiddish, English, Russian, and German, 1893, 1909-1928 (Box 3 (OS1), Folder 1)
  - Russian Theater Books, 1900, 1914-1924 (Box 3 (OS1))
- Series VIII: Photographs, 1924-1926, 1988, undated; 1 manuscript box,; 1 oversize (OS5) box and; 1 oversize (OS2) folder
  This series consists of two boxes of photographs of the Adler family and some of their friends, which have been divided by size and organized by the person pictured, whenever possible. The photos of Celia Adler, Lazar Freed, Jay Adler, Celia’s parents, Dinah Feinman and Jacob Adler, Celia’s sister, Lillie Feinman Satz, and her husband, Ludwig Satz, and Maurice Schwartz were donated by Adler and Freed’s son, Selwyn Freed. There is also a folder of drawings of Lazar Freed and one that appears to have been given to him. In many of the photos of Celia Adler and Lazar Freed, they are in costumes for various performances, sometimes individually and sometimes with a group or on the stage. In addition, in several of the photos of either Adler or Freed when they are not clearly in a costume, they are in a group with others, some of whom have been identified but most of whom remain unidentified. Some of the photos contain unidentified individuals and members of the extended Adler family and friends.
  The photos of Jacob, Sara, Stella, Luther, and Frances Adler, including one with her husband, Joseph Schoengold, who was also an actor, were donated by Ellen Adler. The photos of Sara Adler, Jacob’s third wife, are labeled “Sarah” on the back, although they are photos of his wife, who spelled her name without an ‘h’, rather than of his sister, who spelled her name with an ‘h’. There is also a page of photos of Jacob Adler, which was published by the Forverts after his death in 1926 and which has been removed from Box 4 Folder 16 to an oversize OS2 folder, and photos of a 1988 exhibit on Yiddish theater from the National Museum of American Jewish History in Philadelphia, which displayed many artifacts of Jacob P. Adler. These photos are of individuals, rather than a group. The photos from this donation have not been divided between costumed and non-costumed portraits.
  - Celia Adler, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Celia Adler, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Celia Adler in Costumes, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Celia Adler in Costumes, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Jack (Jay) Adler, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Dinah Feinman and Jacob Adler, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lazar Freed, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lazar Freed, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lazar Freed in Costumes, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Ludwig and Lillie Satz, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Purim Party at Ludwig Satz and Lillie Feinman Satz’s House, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    View the image in Flickr
  - Maurice Schwartz, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Family and Friends, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Frances Adler, with husband, Joseph Schoengold, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Jacob Adler, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Jacob P. Adler in Various Periods of His Life, Forverts, 1926 (Box OS2F-Shared, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit on Jacob Adler at National Museum of American Jewish History in Philadelphia, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Luther Adler, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Sara Adler, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Stella Adler, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Celia Adler, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 1)
  - Celia Adler in Costumes, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 2)
  - Lazar Freed, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 3)
  - Lazar Freed in Costumes, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 4)
  - Lazar Freed in Costumes, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 5)
  - Lazar Freed drawings, 1924, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 6)
  - Ludwig Satz, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 7)
  - Family and Friends, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 8)
  - Jacob Adler, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 9)
  - Luther Adler, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 10)
  - Sara Adler, undated (Box 5 (OS5), Folder 11)
- Series IX: Museum Items, 1916, undated
  This series contains two museum items, a suitcase and a silver calling card holder that is engraved in Yiddish, “For Celia Adler from admirers 1916.” The card holder was donated to AJHS by Michael Steinhardt and the suitcase was donated by Selwyn Freed.
  - Suitcase, undated
  - Celia Adler calling card holder, 1916